[Music]
Welcome Mental Health Monday family.
We're so happy that you are here with us
again this evening. Um hopefully your
week well it just started today but
hopefully you your today Monday was a
good day. I know I had a not as busy and
hectic day I thought. So it was more
relaxing. I still worked but uh wasn't
as busy as I thought it would be. So,
it's Wasn't as manic as usual, you know?
Wasn't as manic as usual. How was yours,
Dr. White? Um, it was it was it had its
little ups and downs, but overall it was
smooth, I would say. All right. Um, it
was overall it was smooth. So, I cannot
complain. I refuse to. Well, that's
good. That's good. And Clint is here.
Good to see you, Clint. But you know,
Scott was here before you were or at
least he wrote in the chat before you
did, Clint. So, I don't know if Scott's
trying to be the first one because I
feel like Yeah, but Scott Scott was here
before you, Clint, but it's always good
to see all of you. Please put in the
chat where you're viewing from. And
before we really start, please put this
on your social media. say, "Hey, if you
guys have mental health questions from a
licensed um psychiatrist and a licensed
therapist, please tune in to mental
health Monday. Invite people and share
this on your social media for sure." Uh
because today, I don't know if you guys
saw the the uh last minute actually
flyer that went out, but we are doing
freestyle mental health Monday. So you
guys are making up this program. Your
questions are uh going to help us do
this program today. So we are we are
answering all mental health questions.
Uh just, you know, we're not your mental
health uh providers, therapists,
psychiatrists, but uh we're going to try
to give you, you know, some some general
answers as we always usually answer
questions. Um but this time we are
taking we don't have a theme. We're
taking all types of questions, mental
health questions and relationship,
marriage questions. So you guys fill up
our chat with questions because we want
to answer those for you and we look
forward uh to doing that. So um man, if
I you know I'm just thinking back like
if I would have you know what honestly
I'm going to take us back. Remember Dr.
Laura? Do you remember Dr. Laura? She
used to absolutely
I used this is way before I even thought
about becoming a mental health
professional like way way before but I
still I used to listen to her. I never
called in but I would like hear her
answer other people's questions. Now
granted I felt like she could be a
little nicer at times.
I hope I hope Yeah. I hope Dr. White and
I are nicer. I think we are. Oh man. She
was she was so to the point, you know,
just really to the point and and yeah,
it was it was funny because she was a
hit on the radio, but then on television
it was so to the point it didn't land
the same, you know? It was So, so radio
and TV are radio and TV are definitely
different different type of audience.
Yeah. It's like you could say like more
maybe
straight to the point kind of hardcore
stuff over the radio a little bit easier
than it like instead of they can't see
you, they can just hear you and they
can't see your facial expression and I
guess also you can't see how the words
are impacting the person, right? So, so
it's it's very interesting but but yeah,
definitely not the approach I've adopted
mostly. No, me neither. Not in therapy
either. But however, she did like for
her raw information, she had some good
stuff. But did you have another favorite
like person that I don't know? I'm
trying to think. I was just thinking in
my head like who did I used to listen to
before I became a mental health? I can't
even think. But Dr. Laura just pops out
in my mind right away. I mean, you got
the Gottman's. I I really like the Got I
liked Gottman. But I actually learned go
about Gottman's once I became um well
when I was in school that's when I
learned about the Gottmans. That's true.
But I definitely but now I listen to a
lot of I I have I love listening to uh
other people especially podcast with
mental health professionals. I love to
there's good like um yeah there's people
that I like. So good. No, good point.
Good point. So yes, but we're glad that
you guys like us, right? So you're here.
Absolutely. Thank you for being here.
So, please um send put some questions in
the chat. Remember, this is freestyle,
meaning like we're taking all mental
health questions. Um again, and we're
also dealing with relationships and
marriage, family,
parenting. It's it's all here, guys.
We're we're we we'll we'll try to tackle
all of it and do our very best, right?
And if you don't ask us questions, we'll
ask each other questions, right?
Yes. Yes, we Yes, we will. We will.
Matter of fact, we might want to start
that start that way. Even though I don't
have a question planned for you, um, let
me I'll ask this question. This is just
to get to know. Okay, there's one before
I could even say it. There it goes. All
right. What are some qualifiers of
trauma? Meaning, how can you identify
trauma? That's a good question, Clint.
That's a great question, Clint. I want
to just take this I'll just I know
you're gonna take a stab at it, too. And
I just want to say that first of all, I
I know that there are
traumas with a capital T and then
there's trauma with like a lowercase T.
But it's still all trauma to that person
whether because people would
think I know even I used to think this
way like you know if you haven't been
sexually assaulted or physically abused
or that type of thing you haven't
suffered trauma, right? Ouch. But that's
far from the truth. Um, trauma can be
being bullied as a kid on the playground
or um, parents not letting not you never
feeling um, like you had the right to
say how you feel about things in a
respectful way. I mean, these are just
examples. I mean, that can be traumatic
for a child and then you grow up still
taking that into your adult life. Um and
so there's there's many different types
of traumas, but um it's you know things
that
um there's not just trauma impacts
everyone differently.
Profound. So you can't just I for you
can't just list it out and say okay if
you have this this and this you've
experienced trauma because everyone
process it differently. What are your
thoughts? What are your thoughts Dr.
White? So, like like you said, I'm going
to echo some of what you said because
you said um there's there's going to be
something of a variance, but I'll say
for example, one level of trauma is when
your boundaries get violated.
Um so, and so now you can see that can
occur on a spectrum. Um you could just
say there's a boundary of not being
talked over, you know, that's slight.
And then there's the boundary of you're
touching me and I didn't ask to be
touched, you know. Um, and you can see
how it can progress from there. Um,
there's also the trauma that's related
to neglect.
Um, one of the most profound things that
happens in relationships is we make
bids.
We make bids. And for those of you in
relationships, especially romantic
relationships, please pay attention to
this, right? We make bids. And what I
mean for example is you walk inside your
home and you
say that's actually a bid right from
jump right but then you say something
like man I've had a hard day
that's a bid right that is a that is it
can be a request for the person to say
okay let me hear you
and and what do people do a lot of times
you had a tough day you should hear
about my day. My goodness, that is an
unanswered bid. And you just I know for
me, I just feel it in my stomach. It's
like my there's a little twinge, you
know, when your bid goes unanswered,
when your bid goes rejected. Um, that's
traumatic, right? That's traumatic. Um,
and it's easy to not sometimes why we
will always champion therapy so much is
sometimes you didn't even know that you
were being impacted by that way. You
just know there's some people it's no
fun to be around. You just know that
there's some people when you're hurting,
you don't want to be near them. And
sorry guys, but a lot of times as
Christians sometimes we'll do this kind
of stuff. President, I have had a rough
day today. You know, if you look in the
Gospel of Mark, chapter 17, you know,
it's like, you know, I love the gospel,
but that's not really what I was talking
about. You should you should think about
how what Christ went through for you.
You know, yet again, another really,
really good point. Christ did do a lot
for me, but right now, I was just hoping
that you would hear me, right? and and
you know and so these are some of the
things that these are some of the ways
that we can not answer bids. It's subtle
and yet profound.
Um and it can be a little on the
traumatic side. And then there is
trauma. There's violating a person's
boundaries. There is assaulting a
person. There is sexual assault. There
is um so trauma is a huge topic, Clint.
It's a huge topic,
but um how do you know your boundaries
are being violated? Your boundaries are
by being violated. Your bids are going
unanswered. Um these are these are some
of the ways that um you can know that
you're you're being traumatized.
Sorry, a little we just addressed five
minutes in a topic that you can get
years of training in trauma. So just
keep this response in that context.
All right. How should a person deal with
a bad feeling of guilt when forgiveness
has already been given?
Hi Deborah, thank you for that question.
And Clint, thank you for your question
as well.
Well, um I see you're still noodling, so
I'll take the first stop.
um
processing it. Yeah, de Deborah first of
all you know thank you for the question
and man on some level I think we all
have to deal with this one you know how
should a person deal with the guilt you
know so here god has extended
forgiveness to us and sometimes that's
the spiritual but in the horizontal
sometimes people have forgiven us and it
is hard to accept it one of the things
that one would explore at that point
Deborah is am I making this about
myself rather than sometimes keeping the
focus on that person. So for example,
keeping the focus on you know Christ has
given me this gift. What if I focused on
that? How awesome that he's given me
this gift. Um what how generous and
maybe maybe the thing that deserves my
focus is understanding that generosity.
Or if it's a human being here, this
human being has meaningfully forgiven
me. What if I direct my focus to that
they've found it in their heart to
forgive me? How generous. Um what are
ways that I can actually celebrate that
and reciprocate it and make sure I never
do that again? And and how generous. So
you can see I can I can operate in the
channel of gratitude, right?
Or I can be selffocused.
I don't deserve that, you know, and I
just can't believe they did it. And one
of the patterns you'll see in the
thoughts is
I I I don't believe it. I don't believe
it. I don't You're making it about you.
And when we focus inward, a lot of times
we can often have problems from just a
focus on ourselves. What are your
thoughts? Yeah. No, I just want to say
Deborah, that is a great question and I
think that, you know, it's to be able to
um receive forgiveness from someone that
you have harmed or did wrong to. um that
can you know that it you you're happy
that they're forgiving you but it is
hard to deal with the the guilt and the
bad thing that you've done. But the
reason why you're the reason why a lot
of times we struggle with uh guilt and
just that emotion is we do feel bad
about it but what happens is that we
have a hard time for allowing ourselves
to forgive ourselves for doing that
thing. When you forgive yourself, you
are actually saying, "I feel so bad that
I've done this." And the only if true
forgiveness for yourself is really the
only way to really move forward with
that is to turn from those ways and
decide, I'm never going to do that
again. I never want to feel I hate this
feeling. I hate the way I've made
somebody else feel and I never want to
do that again. And that's real true
forgiveness for yourself to give
yourself uh the strength and the power
to turn away and never to do that again.
That's profound. But I I in what you
just said though, I heard you have to on
a deep level
feel I have value and I'm worthy of
being forgiven. Yeah, that that's that
can be a real challenge. Yeah, I'm
worthy of being forgiven, you know. And
I mean, this is where Christianity can
be helpful. We are children of a king,
right? Um, and we were redeemed with
blood and not cheap blood. Mhm. No, we
were redeemed with very, very expensive
blood.
Um, so it's a mystery then why we
wouldn't feel worthy. Um, but I I think
that's that's where we we have to start
thinking, no, I'm I am worthy of
forgiveness, you know. I am worthy of
forgiveness. But yeah, again, a huge
huge topic. Yes. Yes. Uh, Clint, these
are some huge topics. Um, next, I'm glad
you and Amber can see the chat because I
can't see the chat unfortunately. I I
did at the beginning, but I can't now,
but that's okay because Amber's managing
that. So, we got you. Yes, Scott.
Dingus. Hello, Scott. He said, "I would
love to discuss divorce and remarry
someone that I'm equally yolked to. I
would like to discuss divorce." All
right. Maybe you could ask a question
about divorce. So, rather than us
launching into something that maybe is
not scratching the itch, what is your
question about divorce that we can
direct some attention to? So, we'll be
looking out for that in the Scott. What
specifically is your question about
divorce? and then then we'll move to
Jason's question in the meantime while
Scott kind of specifies it a little bit.
All right. Um, so Jason said, "What's
the difference of seeing a coach versus
a therapist? Can a coach actually help
with deepseated mental health issues?"
Yeah, great question. That is a good
question. That is a good question
because that that is that is something I
mean coaching is something fairly new
and when I say fairly new um that it's
just very popular right now like life
coaches or health coaches and all these
different areas um the one of the
differences between a mental health
professional and a licensed therapist a
psychiatrist a psychologist is that we
have a a governing board that governs
what we do. meaning we're we actually
are held accountable I should guess I
should say to um a higher uh more than
just ourselves like the coaching
industry is not governed by anyone right
now and I'm sure that that will change
I'm sure that that will change
eventually and because and I'm not
saying that it's it's um that coaches
you know they're it's bad that um
they're not governed by any anyone one
right now, but that's just the reality
of it. So, we um have to license
therapists or mental health
professionals. We have to work by an
ethical standard. Um you know, if we do
something wrong, you could call into our
state board that licensed us and you
know, we can get a a bad report, you
know, that type of thing. But if a coach
does something, there's no one to call
um unless they are, you know, if they
Yeah, there's just nobody to call at
this time. But again, I think that will
change. And so with that said, coaches
have a lot of good things that they can
share and help you with.
Um they haven't been trained in the same
way. Um but it doesn't mean that they
don't have any value at all. And that's
what I'll say about that. What are your
thoughts?
Okay. So there's a different area of
focus. Um, and so while therapists will
focus on healing the past, addressing
mental health issues, trauma, anxiety,
depression, a coach more focuses on
optimizing the present and the future.
True. So, they're going to help with
goals. They're going to improve
performance um and um and they're kind
of achievement
uh focused. Mhm. Um therapists are more
going to be working with somebody with a
di a diagnosis, sometimes dysfunction,
emotional pain that needs treatment,
whereas with a coach, they're working
with clients who are functioning but
want to go from like good to great. Um
so really a coach helps with solving
non-clinical, you know, issues most of
the times.
Um, with therapists, you're going to
hear them do things like CBT, DBT, EMDR,
you know, diagnosis, treatment planning,
that kind of stuff. But, um, again, a a
coach more focused on goal setting,
accountability, strategy building, and
motivational techniques. Um, and I could
go on. Um, therapy requires a license,
LCSW, LPC, U, LCSW, licensed clinical
social worker, right? um or licensed
marriage and family therapists. Um
that's our Atante. Um a psychologist um
or even a psychiatrist like myself. Um
so strict and we're and like you said
it's uh a sister tante we are bound by
strict legal and ethical regulations.
Whereas with coaching, an official
license is not required, though there
are certification programs that exist
and there much fewer legal regulations.
So I can't practice psychiatry. I can't
do psychiatry
um in Maine and places where I'm not
licensed to, right? But coaching I could
do all over the US, you know. So those
are some of the practical differences.
And so then he said, "Oh, go ahead. Go
ahead. Is therapists
um they also have different modalities
that are like solution focused therapy
that would be more like coaching because
it's only solution focused therapy only
focuses on uh the future like if you're
using that modality and therapy like you
know what do you what are your goals?
What do you want to do? So, it's more
like in the system of
coaching, they don't go back and look at
some of the past things that have
brought you to this point. Like in other
therapies, they're going to take a look
at your past and why this, you know, why
maybe you feel stuck and you're not
achieving the goals that you want, those
type of things. But, um, so yeah, so I
would say that honestly in therapy there
is a lot of coaching that's going on,
but there's a lot of other things going
on as well. Um, right.
Because yeah, there there's a point in
therapy where we do want the person to
be more future oriented and sometimes
they're starting to thrive and so now
you're going to shift your focus to more
coaching styled. Okay, well now let's
build on that. And you do heal at some
point. And so and the person will still
say, "Hey, I want to grow more." And now
you can continue to build. And
sometimes, of course, you're going to do
more coaching. So more a coaching
approach than a therapy approach. So as
a patient
heals, you're allowed to do more
coaching. But I think as a therapist is
more able to understand the difference
between, okay, now the person's healed,
so now we can do more of a coaching
approach. Right. Absolutely. I love this
qu next question. I'd like to take a
stab. Um, I studied journalism,
uh, but bad but bad news, uh, affects my
mental health in some ways. I'm not
practicing my profession. How can I deal
with this Jacqueline? Oh, okay.
Jacqueline. Yes,
that's a good question and I the reason
why it it I wanted to take a stab at it
because I studied journalism too and um
that was my first love. That was my very
first love was to do journalism. That's
all I ever wanted to do. And then, you
know, life in the journey of life, God
brought me into mental health. And there
was a time before I got into mental
health where I definitely felt like,
man, I'm not following what I originally
wanted to do and to deal with that. But
you're saying that like just working in
the news industry affects your your
mental health. And that's look with us
watching the news, it affects our mental
health. So you're not alone in that. it
can affect our mental health because
there's so um so many sad things uh that
are happening just like one after one
and then working in that industry. So
it's really about perspective
um because I'll say this as a mental
health professional I don't know you
probably get this question a lot too Dr.
I people say, "Isn't it really sad and
hard to listen to people's problems all
day long?" And I'm like, you know, and
I, you know, I really tell people it's
not being a mental health professional
is not for everyone. It really isn't. I
feel
like I don't know. It's just like
because there's certain I'm use my
husband as an example. I always use him
as an example. He should watch Mental
Health Monday more. You'd see I use him
as an example often, but he is a
very deeply empathetic person. Like I
could see I couldn't see my husband's a
pastor. You It's funny that I would say
this, but and he can pastor and give
therapy on like a certain level and not
but if he had to hear the things that I
hear on a daily basis, he would just be
crying all day long. That's how
empathetic he is, you know? Like he just
can't. And I'm not saying I'm not
empathetic, but it's just, you know, I
guess when you're there for when you put
yourself in the place, well, this is
where this is the place you are in. But
when you put yourself in a place that
they need my help, they need me to, you
know, they're here for me to to help
them, you know, and so with that
mindset, I I'm hearing the painful
things they're sharing. Um,
but I'm able to process it and because I
feel like because I'm not in the
situation, I will have some answers for
them to help them even though I'm being
very empathetic with with them, but try
to help them to get through this. So I
said all that to say that if that is too
much for you, there's nothing wrong um
with stepping away and and maybe doing
journalism in a different way um where
maybe you're not producing helping to
produce the news with all the sad
stories, but you're able to in some way
be a do journalism and and provide
information without producing negative
sad stories. Okay, that's my shot.
What's your answer? Well, first and
foremost,
you you were you were hitting it and
like it's and you you you're kind of
going to say everything I just said, but
you just said it in a different way.
Okay.
Um, you know, and I know that when
people come into you, they don't leave
the same way, right? You know, you and
and I and I know you're a phenomenal
therapist and I know the way they came
in, they often don't leave. That's why
we can do what we do, right? Because
it's not like we're just hearing sad
stories and sad stories and like no,
it's like you wouldn't believe the power
of informed words. You wouldn't believe
it. You wouldn't believe the ability to
reframe. Now, take Hua King for example.
Um, yes, I would listen and hear, hey,
how is the news impacting you? And why
is that? And why does it position you
that that way? Um, and and we would
really delve into it. But at its core,
journalism is just like medicine, which
is just like law, which is just like
nursing. It's so broad. It's so broad.
So there's there's once you decide I
don't like negative news like don't you
wish we developed the GNN network the
good news network like don't you love
those network called that probably I
wouldn't be surprised I wouldn't be
surprised like imagine so we could find
those stories that are so inspirational
so inspirational you take the ugliest
tragedy. There's always these stories
that just make you just give you chills.
The generosity, the courage, the it's
it's always there. Maybe we that's your
calling that you find the beauty even in
the ugliest situations, right? And and
that's impactful, you know, or you just
focus on beautiful situations. You find
the beauty in the beautiful situations
and you bring that to our attention.
Because I tell you right now, sometimes
when you listen to news, it tempts you
to lose your belief in the beauty of the
human story, but it's always there. It's
always there. It's a world of good and
evil. Good. There will there will be
evil, but you're always going to be able
to find some good. And this is one of
the things that I know I encourage my
patients with that as as bad as that
there are things that have happened if
you pay attention there are some good
things that are happening as well.
And I was just going to say this I know
it's going to another question but the
joy that we
receive when you see a client or patient
the light bulbs go off or they're
getting better and they just have made a
perspective change and a change in their
life. It's worth the hours of, you know,
listening
to different, you know, different
negative things to see them grow. It's
just, it's worth it. Like I know I leave
feeling very fulfilled. So, exactly.
Exactly. It It's funny, Shereice, you
go, "How do mental health professionals
handle their own mental health?" A lot
of mental health professionals are um go
to therapy, but the the funny thing
about it is I'm not a therapist.
you you had to just out it like that,
right? Um Well, because when I was
taught in school like No, with this with
the school, I mean, I went to they um
you had to have an at least to graduate,
you had to have at least I forgot how
many hours of your own therapy so that
you would know what it felt like when
your clients to come to sit down and to
be able to to share. And I thought that
was great because it was a good
experience to just have to be on the
other side of things. But no, but
therapists need therapists. It's great.
We have to keep our own mental health
good. No question. And it's like a
maintenance thing, you know? I f I make
it a point to find people who I know
listen well. Like I I'll say that
because that's ultimately what I what I
like. People who can who do a really
nice job listening. that that to me is
um super helpful. Um I can't say I go to
my therapist all the time, but I have
one. So when I need to talk to someone,
we're already established. You know what
I mean? So, right, you you have your
mental health team in place before the
crisis, which is super smart. Super
smart. Exactly. Now, the other really
funny thing is you would think the hard
part is the the the sickness that we
find in the therapeutic setting. And
what's interesting, shares, is it's
actually the stressors around that that
if anything are the most frustrating
things, you know, whether it's, you
know, third party payers or, you know,
just like you you wouldn't believe the
things around that because, as I was
explaining to my mother the other day,
like when you're in front of that
patient
and you get an opportunity to help them
create some value Mhm. And and you see
them come in broken and walk out a
different person. Yes. It's It's really
like you It doesn't keep you down. It If
anything, it it it Yeah. You Yeah. It's
dopamine. It's probably like a It's a
dopamine hit. Like, you know, it's like
we feel good. It's spiritual. It's like
It's just amazing. It's It's an absolute
amazing feeling to to be a resource to a
person. So no, it's not people just
coming in broken and you just observing
them and leaving them broken. You you
help them on their path to healing. And
then that's amazing. It's absolutely
amazing. It is. It is.
Amra, how do I overcome haunting
memories from my past from times I was
an alcoholic? I capture my thoughts. I
give them to God. Remind myself that I'm
a new creation. But how do I overcome
the spiritual attack?
That formula that you just put is
what what it what it really is. You said
you capture your thoughts. I love that.
Give them to God and remind yourself who
you are. And that is just on
repeat. I mean that just goes on repeat
because
um those memories are are still there.
and and you doing that over and over and
over again. And I'm sure over time it's
become less and less and less, but
you're saying it hasn't gone away
completely, but I believe that's still
the recipe for success in that area. No.
Well said. Um, you you said it, Sister
Tanta, you said it, Amra, and you know,
I'll I will add this to that.
Um, you cannot erase memories, but you
can crowd them out. Yeah, you can crowd
them out. Um, memories, the essence of
memories is the patterning of our minds.
So, there's a thing called
neuroplasticity. Um, and so there are
neural networks. They're grooves like
think of the highway and and you know,
but there are grooves. And the more we
think, the more we hardwire those um
those those grooves and those networks,
the more we think about that thing, the
less we think about it,
um the the softer the grooves get and
the and the neuroplasticity diverts
itself to the things you're actually
dedicating your thoughts to.
So,
Amra, an important strategy is build new
meaningful memories. Yes. Awesome,
beautiful, powerful memories like that
beautiful man you're married to, right?
You know, it's like you create memories,
you know, with them. I really admire you
guys' relationship. I admire your story.
Um, and it's it's something beautiful
that you're doing, you know, and it's
just generate the memories that crowd
out those awful, you know, memories. Uh,
and as far as these dark memories, the
the true purpose for revisiting a memory
is when you can draw power from it. Is
when you can draw power. And if you
can't draw power from it, leave it
alone. The day may come when you can,
but if you emerge from a memory feeling
weaker, that's a hint. Leave it alone.
It it doesn't have a space in your
future. Um, and you you leave it alone
and create new memories. Right. This is
why sometimes it's not the best idea to
keep reciting those old stories and it's
not always the best idea. Yeah. um build
new sober stories. Sober um stories that
are so awesome, so voluminous
that they just crowd out the memory and
you are taking up the real estate.
You're occupying the real estate with
new sticky powerful meaningful memories.
Absolutely.
Another Do you use CBT? Do you use CBT?
Um CBT
I cognitive behavioral therapy. Yes. But
go ahead. You can go ahead. I do. I do
in my Yeah. So CBT is cognitive
behavioral therapy and it's based on the
premise
that your mood impacts your thoughts and
your thoughts impact your mood. Um so
that if you want to change you know your
mood you got to change your thoughts.
Yes. And ultimately CBT gets at the
linkage between your thoughts and your
moods and your thoughts patterns. And so
it has you do things like interrogate
your thinking. Is it valid? Well, then
we have to abandon it. It's very
systematic. Uh so it absolutely has its
place. It's incredibly wellstudied. I
don't think you can mention CBT without
um discussing Aaron Beck uh the founder
of CBT. And now, of course, his daughter
has taken up the charge. You remember
her name? I don't remember her name.
Something Beck. It's something. I don't
know if it's Linda Beck. I I forget her
name, but she's definitely taking up the
charge. Yeah. No, I definitely use CBT
every day probably with clients. I mean,
in
some way, shape, and form just to again
to have them to just become more aware
of their thoughts and their feelings and
then their behavior. Um and yeah and
like what you said challenging those
thoughts those negative those automatic
negative thoughts like we the automatic
negative thoughts for the majority of
our life have never really been
challenged for most people right they
just let them like fire off and we just
accept them. But when you're
understanding
uh those negative thoughts are what
create your mood and then your behavior
and that once you become aware of the
negative thoughts you're like wait a
minute I can actually start to
interrogate these thoughts put them on
trial get new thoughts you know and and
then like you said the neuroplasticity
um we can have our brains can change our
thought process can change um and so
that is one of the therapies that when I
use that it's just like it's they
clients just feel so empowered because
they're like I can have power over these
negative thoughts because for most of
their life they just felt like well I'm
just a slave to this you know this is
just how it has to be and what CBT helps
to helps people with is to realize that
it doesn't have to be that way this this
is why reflective writing is so powerful
um and sometimes if you just like write
a brain dump. If you just write and
write, I I know when I'm really furious,
when something has really angered me,
man, it is so cathartic to just write
right right. And then I look, I'm like,
and there's no editing, right? There's
no editing. So, I do it next to a
shredder so that like I can write to my
heart's content and make sure nobody's
gonna find this, you know, and then I
just shred it. And it's just it just
feels so cathartic. But the the point is
like you're you're like I didn't know I
was thinking this way. Um, now those are
the thoughts that you don't want anybody
to find. And then other times you're
just journaling your thoughts. Sometimes
your dreams, your aspirations, and it's
it's so interesting when you read it cuz
you're like, I didn't know I was
reading. I didn't know I felt that way.
And a really cool thing is sometimes
years later when you revisit it you're
like really I was thinking that you know
um so without that kind of intention you
might never realize the thoughts that
are swirling around your head that are
connected to your emotions and more
important than that that are connected
to your actions. Right. So something to
think about now Mr. Sneaky. I know Mr.
Sneaky. That's Wow, Mr. Sneaky. Um,
okay. Listen to this question. It says,
"I've always felt like needing therapy
means God isn't enough to comfort me.
How do how do I view this?" Or are you
asking how do we view this or how how
should he view it? Or how should you
view this? How should he view it? Yeah.
Well, obviously we're Christian mental
health therapists or mental health
professionals. So um we we definitely
believe that we can be used but along
with what God is trying to do in your
life and God obviously it to me is the
ultimate ultimate uh mental health um
therapist for everybody right
but he can use humans and other humans
to help you in your mental health
journey and it doesn't mean to go to
therapy that you are uh discrediting
what God could do because I believe that
what
therapists can do is again help to um
work along with what God is wanting
positive things that God wants to do in
your life. Like he wants you to have
positive
um thinking and and and not automatic
negative thinking and things like that
along with a lot of other things that
you may be dealing with. And so just
like a doctor, I mean, God can heal. He
could just touch us and heal us, right?
But he allows us to be able to go to
human medical doctors that can can help
us um along the way. And the same thing
is with the mental health professionals.
We we by no means replace God um in your
life. And you're not weak if you go to a
mental health professional because you
are a Christian. And so whatever a
mental health professional is telling
you or or you guys are dealing with, you
can still process that through uh your
Christian understanding of what God
wants for you and wants to do in your
life. What are your thoughts, Dr. White?
Well, thank you for validating that,
especially as a pastor's wife. You know,
um you know what's funny? Um with this
question, Mr. Sneaky, I would refer you
to one of the first therapeutic
interventions found in scripture. And we
actually find it in Genesis. The the
setup for it is where in Genesis, God
literally says, "It is not good for the
man to be alone." He literally says
that. Mhm. Well, one of the things that
happens in
companionship is people being able to
hear one another effectively. But now,
when you think about our first parents,
Adam and Eve, their emotional
intelligence is off the chain.
In
fact, after the fall,
Eve is feeling pretty bad because she
has just ushered in death.
And up to that point, her name was
woman. The therapeutic intervention is
where Adam then says, "Look, your new
name is Eve, mother of all living."
Here, this person has just ushered in
death, but he renames her Eve, mother of
all living. So in the face of such of an
ugly event, notice the intervention.
That's not a surgical intervention.
That's not a physical intervention. That
is a
psychotherrapeutic intervention, right?
And it it it begs the question, man, how
are you impacting the people in your
life in the midst of their mistakes?
What are you calling them? So my point
being, God invented
psychotherapy. He invented it. Um, he
invented our ability to help one another
with words, observation, and insight.
Yes. Excellent. Very good. We have
Ashley asking, "So, I'm a I'm new to the
health message, and I listened uh to
much of EG White. I'm very sick, so I'm
trying to follow her counsel, but I'm in
I'm in an unsupportive environment. any
advice? So, what I'm hearing, Ashley, is
that you are having some you're very
sick, so you're having some health
issues. Um, and your environment, uh,
whatever that is, um, is is not really
supporting you in your journey and
trying to follow the counsel that, um,
through the health message. So that can
be very very difficult when you don't
have the emotional support um to make
changes in your lifestyle. Um so I mean
unless people are physically stopping
you from doing things I mean if this is
a decision that you have made for
yourself and for your health you can't
really look to others for validation.
You know what I mean? You have to if
like this is for your health. This is
you said you're very sick. So this is
for your life, right? This is for you to
to to feel well and to be well and not
to be saved in the kingdom like this
makes you a better Christian, but for
your physical for your physical health.
All right. Did you guys see the
balloons? Did you see those balloons? I
saw those balloons. I'm so glad you said
that because I'm not imagining things.
That's great.
No. So I'm sorry, Ashley. But back to
this. So, um, again, you're not looking
again, if people aren't physically
stopping you from eating this way and
and maybe they're always I don't know.
It sounds like I don't know if they're
mocking you for the way that you're
eating or or teasing the fact that
you're not eating how they're eating. I
I'm not sure. But either way, you have
to block out all that negative noise and
always on a daily basis, it sounds like
you're living in that situation. um
remind yourself why you are doing what
you're doing and what you're doing is
what's going to help you to be um as
healthy as you can be. I mean you're
sick and so maybe it's helping you feel
better. It's you know it's helping you
in your journey. I mean it's
unfortunate that
um you know someone would would mock you
or not make it easy for you when you're
sick. But um you're in that situation
and I'm sure if you could not be in that
situation it sounds like maybe you
wouldn't be. So since you have to sounds
like you have to be in that situation
the only thing you can control you can't
control them. So let them do them and
but you can control how you respond and
how you process what they are saying and
doing. Um but you keep moving forward
and do the healthy things for you. What
are your thoughts Dr. White?
I don't think there's a lot to add to
that to be honest with you. Okay. No.
Well well done. Yeah. So Ashley, hope
you feel better. Sorry that you're not
feeling well. Hope you feel better.
All right. So, Scott Dingan said, "How
to overcome
schizoeffect schizoeffective disorder
and psychotic depression." All right.
So, you're talking about um notice now
these are diagnos well especially
schizopeffective disorder and it usually
has a subtype whether depressed type or
bipolar type. So these are diagnosis
and you can see that this requires
professional treatment. So Scott, it's
it can often be a
combination of um correct
diagnosis and then there can be a
therapeutic element to the intervention
and there can be a
pharmacotherrapeutic you know element to
the diagn uh to the intervention.
And there's also a very important
role of medical assessment to make sure
that
um other things have ruled out to make
sure you have the correct diagnosis. Um
but there's there's a role for medical
intervention because you have the
sunlight, you have the exercise, you
have the good sleep hygiene, you have um
good diet, you know. So I just want you
to see the comprehensive nature that is
involved in getting a great outcome and
it's it's not just meds, it's not just
therapy um necessarily. It is a
combination of of all those things so
that a person gets great care, right? Um
absolutely. But no, great question.
Yeah, you want to know that um uh with
schizopeeffective disorder, you're
you're talking about this kind of
combination of both um psychosis as well
as a mood component. Um psychosis is a
big word for a person is having trouble
distinguishing between what's real and
what's not real. And then with the mood
component, you're saying there can be
depression. Um, and so there's symptoms
that are characterized by depression and
then there's bipolar. Um, and so with
there there's an there can be an
elevation in the mood that more
characterizes that bipolar component.
Um, and then with uh psychotic
depression, I've already defined
psychosis, but depression can progress
to the point of severity to where it's
actually associated with elements of
psychosis. So a person a person's
depression can get to the point where
they're having trouble distinguishing
between what's real and what's not real.
So at that level of complexity
um there need there can be so many
interventions that are necessary up to
and including whether it's um
electroconvulsive shock therapy or deep
brain stimulation or just a host of
other things. Um but again a lot of
times when we think about mental illness
we'll think about the light stuff you
know that that maybe we are seeing or
that we think of a lot of times we don't
imagine the super severe mental illness
um where life a person's life is at risk
because um suicidal uh ideiation and
self harm behavior do often accompany
psychiatric illness as well. So um it's
something that deserves a full
complement of creative intervention
professional. just want to add like when
I have um when I have people come in and
they have been diagnosed with the you
know schizoeffective
um I if they're
not you know and it's not just but if
they're in that family of disorders if
they're not currently taking their meds
it's like it's impossible and they're
not regulated excuse me and they're not
taking their meds it's it's impossible
for me to do talk therapy or to do
psychotherapy
because they need it. You know, I can do
psychotherapy when they're on their meds
and they're, you know, balancing out,
but um it's it's very difficult to do
and to be effective if they're not on
their meds.
Well, thank you for that context. How do
you heal when your family has always
used you as a scapegoat? The one that
took the family trauma. It's like there
was not
affection in the mentally ill. Um
having trouble with that question. Okay.
Oh, I see what she Okay. Or I'm sorry,
not Sherry. Um it's like there was not
affected like she was the mentally ill
one causing Oh. Oh, okay. Okay. I see. I
see. So, isn't like there's I I see. So
I mean there are family dynamics. There
are family dynamics where at times
there's a person who's identified as a
problem when in fact the whole family
unit has a problem and they're
scapegoating that person saying well fix
her and everything will be okay when in
fact that's like I I I see now better
you know what you're um saying Sherry.
Um, Sherry, uh, I think,
um, I I
think this is where it's so critical
then that you kind of set your goals.
You get you set your goals for your
life. Um, and then more than likely in
the partnership with um, you know, a
professional mental health practitioner,
so whether it's a therapist or or what
have
you, you get clear now on
Do I have an issue that needs support?
And
then what are my goals so that I
understand what boundaries I need to set
in order to achieve those goals. Um, and
you can see why it is incredibly
difficult to provide advice in that
context because we don't know your
situation. like your well-being might be
dependent on this in the situation that
you're and so you now have to figure out
hey what are the boundaries I need to
set what are the goals that I have and
how do I work towards that and so
customization is just something so
important in effective mental
intervention sure we might know the
theories but applying them to your
specific
situation that's
where that one-on-one you know or that
customized is
um strategizing is critical. Um but but
great great opportunity for us at least
to mention that it's a very interesting
dynamic where at times you know there's
this false identifying of this is the
problem when in fact even if there is a
problem there there is a problem in the
family system that might need to be
addressed.
It's definitely a family um it's in the
family system and that's why a good
mental health professional um and
someone who will even do family therapy
and and it would be amazing if the
family would go to family therapy and
really address this if there was wanting
to be healing. But it sounds like you're
you're talking about healing just for
yourself because I don't know if the
family dynamics is even willing or open
to even thinking okay it could be you
know we need to look at this um as a
family instead of just one person. Um
but definitely getting mental health
professional help for you um would be
very good at this time. If your family
never goes, that's too bad for them. But
if you go, uh, you can definitely start
the process of
healing. But it's a great question,
Sherry. Thank you. All right, it looks
like we have time for one more
question. Is the love deeply
emotional sad music? Oh, to love deeply
emotional sad music. I didn't see the
last part and it switched out. Okay. Is
the love deeply to love is the love
deeply emotional sad music a sign of
depression? I would no it's not a sign
of depression. Um some people are more
melancholy. Um I can tell you my husband
and I our music tastes are completely
different as far as like you know I he
he just loves different music than I do
as far as it's more because he's more of
a melancholic person. So his music vibe
is more matching to his personality type
where mine
is, you know, just more upbeat and
flower. Like he likes things that let
you make you think and meditate and, you
know, he's always in deep thought about
something. He likes his music to be on
that level. It doesn't mean he's not
depressed. He just likes emotional
music. Man, he feels the music deeper
than I do. Man after my own heart. Yeah,
I like I like music that has the power
to lift me from, you know, lift me from,
let's say, even like sadness. And yeah,
my my wife Florence, like she likes
uppidity music is what I call it. And
they all know, they all know. No, no,
skip skip this
one. But they they know me. Um
uh but yeah, it's I don't know. There's
something about music that makes you
think. So I I really can identify with
him. When we first got married, I
remember we'd be in the car and he'd
play his music and I was like, "Uh, can
you turn that?" And then after like
several times that he's like, "You don't
love my music." I'm like, "No, it makes
me sad
or makes me think about sad things." You
know what I mean? Like it's just
different. Like it makes him happy.
That's funny. My wife is such a smart
eye. Like she's like watching right now
and so she's like, "I can't imagine what
you've written about me." like such a
smart because of my comment from before.
That's funny. Okay, we have time for one
more. So, if there's another question,
I don't know if there is another one.
That might have been the last one.
And that was from Sister Joanne. I
didn't look who that was from, but no,
Sister Joanne, it's not not a sign of
depression. Didn't know the name of that
one. Okay, I don't think we we may not
have another one. It ends right. That
would be perfect timing. I don't know
about you, but I had a lot of fun. I
Yeah, this was this was amazing. Great
idea. Didn't feel the stress. We didn't
have a topic. It was just free. Great
idea. Freestyle. Great idea. So, I think
we'll do this more often. I mean, we're
definitely going to have our topics, but
we'll definitely be able to put this in
maybe once a month. We'll see. I mean,
we have to talk about it, but I said a
lot of questions. You guys had a lot of
questions and it was a well-rounded
um topics that came up. So, thank you.
Thank you everyone. Please again share
this on your social media because even
if they weren't here live, they can
still see it. It's going to be of course
on YouTube, but uh put it on your
Facebook and where just wherever on your
Instagram. Please share, share, share
because this is you guys had great
questions and by God's grace we gave you
know some some good answers.
Always a pleasure, sister Tante. Till
next time. Yes, do you too. Okay,
everyone. Have a good night. Bye. Bye.